## **GAURAV SOOD**

#### Sr. Data Scientist



**J** +91 9632714987

Bangalore, India

github.com/gsood-gaurav



"Senior Data Scientist with total 14 years of experience, and 7 years of experience in Machine Learning, developing open source software in Python, C++, contributing as both individual contributor and team leader, working on Machine Learning, conceptualizing, designing and implementing end to end solutions. Currently working on ideas around Natural Language Processing and Reinforcement Learning to automate Hardware Diagnostics. Have used both traditional machine learning methods like Bayesian Networks, Conditional Random Fields and modern deep learning methods LSTMs, Transformer based models like BERT and GPT, using TensorFlow Recently started using Julia and Flux for Machine Learning."

### **SKILLS**

| Python PyTorch TensorFlow JAX Julia Flux NumPy SciPy Matplotlib                                    |  |  |  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
|--|--|--|--|--|--|--|--|--|--|
| Deep Learning Large Language Models Generative AI Probabilistic Programming Reinforcement Learning |  |  |  |  |  |  |  |  |  |
| Open Source Software   |  |  |  |  |  |  |  |  |  |

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Sr. Data Scientist

#### HP Inc. June 2021 - Ongoing

- **B**angalore, India
- Designed and Developed Large Language Models Based application for web content filtering/selection.
- Mentored three data science interns on Hardware logs analysis using Graph Neural Networks and Large Language Models.
- Fine Tuned Small language Chat model on custom data using 4-bit quantized models.
- Developed Telemetery data analysis pipline using Large Language Model embeddings, UMAP, Variational AutoEncoder.

| •                       |                    |                       |                 |                         |
|-------------------------|--------------------|-----------------------|-----------------|-------------------------|
| Probabilistic modelling | Gaussian processes | Variational inference | Optimal control | Trajectory optimisation |
|                         |                    |                       |                 |                         |

#### Software Engineer Machine Learning

#### HP Inc. June 2017 - 2021

- **B**angalore, India
- Analyzed Sales Time Series Data (Short term/Long term forecasting) using Prophet, ARIMA, Gradient Boosting models.
- Behavior Modelling using Tree Based Models, SHAP, UMAP
- Proposed methodology which specifies automated hardware diagnostics problem in Reinforcement Learning Framework
- Design and implemented software module which models environment for Reinforcement Learning agent to learn using Monte Carlo Methods.
- Worked on Conditional Random Fields for Sequence Tagging and Information extraction.

| Communication   Active listening | Teaching |      |      |      |
|----------------------------------|----------|------|------|------|
| 1. Senior Software Engineer      |          |      |      |      |
|                                  |          | <br> | <br> | <br> |

## Senior Software Engineer

HP Inc. June 2015 - 2017

**B**angalore, India

- Designed and Developed a parser for PostScript Language to extract images and meta data which was impacting 50000 hp customers and saving 5 million dollars.
- Designed and developed Telemetery module in python.
- Led team of 7 software developers designing and implementing open source software used by over 1 million customers
- Worked on understanding PDF specification, design and implemented PDF document processing using PDF libraries like iText and PDFium
- Lead a team of six people which delived Imaging Processing Solutions to over 10 PSU banks in india

Engineering | Teamwork | Industry

2. Software Engineer

Software Engineer

HP Inc. June 2010 - 2015

**B**angalore, India

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

Deep Learning Specialization

Coursera Oct-2021 Credential ID G8PG2GY6WFS)

Reinforcement Learning Specialization

Coursera Sept-2021 Credential IDD3LDNU8BRW68

Introduction to Quantum Computing
Coursera May-2021 Credential ID RXQHLEC2WYC8

### **PROJECTS**

Optimal Control in Multimodal Dynamical Systems as Probabilistic Inference University of Bristol

May 2021 - Ongoing

Bristol, UK

- Developing data-efficient techniques for exploration in multimodal dynamical systems.
- The goal of this project is to explore a single dynamics mode that is known to be operatable whilst avoiding other modes.

Variational inference | Gaussian processes

Optimal control

## PROJECTS (CONT.)

## Trajectory Optimisation in Learned Multimodal Dynamical Systems

#### **University of Bristol**

**Sept 2019 - March 2021** 

- Bristol, UK
- Synergising Bayesian inference and Riemannian geometry to control multimodal dynamical systems.
- Finds trajectories that 1) remain in a desired dynamics mode, 2) avoid regions of the dynamics with high epistemic uncertainty.
- **Q** aidanscannell/trajectory-optimisation-in-learned-multimodal-dynamical-systems

JAX Probabilistic geometries Optimal control

#### Identifiable Mixtures of Sparse Variational Gaussian Process Experts

#### **University of Bristol**

Sept 2018 - Ongoing

- Bristol, UK
- Improving identifiability and scalability in the Mixtures of Gaussian Process Experts model with GP-based gating networks.
- Variational inference based on sparse GP approximations.
- Q aidanscannell/mogpe

GPflow TensorFlow Gaussian processes Variational inference

### VOLUNTEERING

#### **Cohort Representative**

#### **FARSCOPE CDT**

Sept 2018 - Ongoing

- Bristol, UK
- Represent myself and my CDT peers in management meetings.
- Communicate information between students and management.

Communication | Interpersonal Skills

#### Club Leader

#### **Code Club**

Dec 2017 - April 2018

- Junction 3 Library, Bristol, UK
- Set up (and then ran) a Code Club for children aged 9-13.
- Led the organisation, planning and teaching of weekly lessons.
- Planned lessons to engage children by making coding fun.
- Extremely rewarding and reinforced my love for teaching.

 Leadership
 Teaching
 Communication
 Active listening

## **INVITED TALKS**

## Synergising Bayesian Inference and Probabilistic Geometries for Robotic Control

Cognitive Systems - Technical University of Denmark (DTU)

**18 March 2021** 

Zoom

Presented a method synergising Bayesian inference and probabilistic geometries to control multimodal dynamical systems.

Communication

Probabilistic geometries

Gaussian processes

## **EDUCATION**

Msc Research Speech Recoginition

**Indian Institute of Science Bangalore 2006-2009** 

## MEng in Mechanical Engineering University of Bristol | First Class Honours

**Sept 2012 - June 2016** 

- Graduated in top 10% of cohort

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>Awarded if PhD is not completed.

## **ACHIEVEMENTS**

# Full Sporting Colours

Awarded full colours for outstanding achievements in snowboarding. Multiple gold medals in British University Snowboard Championships.



#### **Starting To Teach**

Established myself as a confident, enthusiastic and effective teacher who is able to engage, encourage and develop students' learning.



## Bristol Plus Award

For undertaking a wide range of tasks to further enhance student skills - only 700 out of 23,000 achieved this award per annum.



#### **Mary Jones Prize for Mathematics**

For outstanding achievements in A Level mathematics @ Ripon Grammar School



#### The Duke of Edinburgh's Award

Bronze/Silver/Gold

## REFERENCES

#### **Prof. Arthur Richards**

@ University of Bristol

■ arthur.richards@bristol.ac.uk

#### Dr. Carl Henrik Ek

@ University of Cambridge